Lucy Suchman's 1985 book "Plans and Situated
Actions," is the seminal book on the philosophy of situated action.
The book is a detailed comparison between two views of human action.
The first view she writes views
the organization insignificance of action as derived from plans.
This is the model we very often adopt when developing interfaces.
Users make plans and users carry out those plans.
But such then introduces a second view as well.
In this view, people simply act in the world,
and plans are what we derive from those actions.
Instead of plans dictating actions,
plans are interpretations of actions.
What this means for us as interface designers is that rather than
assuming the user has a plan in mind that they're actively carrying out,
we might consider viewing
only their immediate interaction with the current screen instead.
In other words, forget the history of actions that
led the user to a certain screen and ask just,
"Once they're here, how do they know what to do next?
Later in the book, Lucy Suchman specifically touches
on communication between humans and machines.
There's a lot more depth here as well.
The key takeaway for us is to focus on
the resources available to the user at any given time,
but I do recommend reading the book and this chapter for more insights.