In this lesson, we've covered three theories on studying
contexts in human-computer interaction: distributed cognition,
situated action, and activity theory.
If you're having trouble keeping the three straight though,
Nardi has a great paper for you.
From her volume context and consciousness,
Nardi wrote a comparison between the three philosophies she titled
"Studying Context: A Comparison of Activity Theory,
Situated Action Models, and Distributed Cognition."
She starts by giving a great one-page summary of each of these three views,
which would be really good if you're having trouble
understanding the finer points of these theories.
Even more usefully, she goes on to give
commentary on the difference between these three big theories.
First, she notes that activity theory and distributed cognition are driven by goals,
whereas situated action de-emphasizes goals for a focus on improvisation.
She goes on to summarize the situated actions as goals are
constructed retroactively to interpret our past actions.
Nardi also evaluates the role of permanent persistent structures,
noting they're important for activity theory and distributed cognition,
but present a tension for situated action.
So, here, we again see a similarity between activity theory and distributed cognition.
So, what makes them different?
Well, Nardi writes that the main difference between activity theory and
distributed cognition is their evaluation of the symmetry between people and artifacts.
Activity theory regards them as fundamentally different,
given that humans have consciousness.
Distributed cognition by contrast believes that artifacts can serve cognitive roles,
and so those should be considered conceptually equivalent to humans.
So, that gives a high-level overview of the difference between these three theories.
These theories are big and complex, of course,
and the complete paper goes into much more detail.
But this should provide a decent glimpse at
the distinctions at least enough to get you started reading the paper for yourself.