In a recent paper, in The Washington and Lee Law Review,
Molly Jackman and Lauri Kanerva,
two Facebook employees explored exactly this issue.
Jackman and Kanerva specifically note that
the ethical guidelines developed in the context of academia,
do not always address some of the considerations of industry.
In response, the authors directly advocate for setting up
a set of principles and practices for industry environments.
In other words, rather than just ignoring the parts that aren't relevant for industry,
the authors advise creating a new set of standards specifically for industry.
To do so, Facebook designed its own internal review process.
In this case, Facebook's process is heavily
reliant on deferring to a research area expert.
I don't say defer in a bad way.
A key part of IRB is that experiments are reviewed by
people with no incentive to permit the study if it isn't ethical.
Facebook tries to replicate this by referring studies to
an external reviewer who in turn decides whether or not an additional review,
and even external IRB is necessary.
The other thing that's important to note though,
is that Facebook isn't under any strong obligation to do this.
Universities that receive federal funding are governed by the Belmont Report,
but companies are not yet governed by any similar law.
So we rely on companies to govern themselves.
In Facebook's case, it seems to be going pretty well,
but you might find yourself at a company that doesn't have
such a program and you'll have to apply these standards yourself.