Batya Friedman is one of the co-directors of
the Value Sensitive Design Research Lab at the University of Washington,
and she co-authored one of the seminal papers on the topic,
Value Sensitive Design and Information Systems.
Friedman, Khan and Borning together provide this excellent paper on the philosophy.
In it, they cover three investigations for approaching value sensitive design.
First, the cover conceptual investigations.
Conceptual investigations are like thought experiments where we explore
the role values play in questions like who are the direct and indirect stakeholders,
and how are both classes of stakeholders affected?
Second, they cover empirical investigations.
Empirical investigations go out and use real users,
exploring how they make sense of interfaces and answering questions like
how do stakeholders apprehend individual values in the interactive context?
How do they prioritize individual values and usability considerations?
Third, they cover technical investigations.
Technical investigations are like empirical investigations that target the systems,
instead of the users.
They ask the same kind of questions but they're especially targeting whether or
not the systems are compatible with the values of the users.
The paper also proposes some of the fundamental features of value sensitive design.
For example, value sensitive design should be proactive
and values sensitive design distinguishes between usability and human values.
If you're playing to work in an area where human values play a significant role,
and I would argue that, that's probably most areas of HCI,
I highly recommend reading through this paper.
It can have a profound impact not only on the way you design
interfaces but on the way you approach user research.