In 2006, Stephanie Chamberlain, Helen Sharp, and
Neil Maiden investigated the conflicts and
opportunities of applying agile development to user-centered design.
They found interestingly that the two actually had a signficant overlap.
Both agile development and user-centered design emphasized
iterative development processes building on feedback from previous rounds.
That's the entire design life cycle that we've talked about.
That's at the core of both agile development and user-centered design.
Both methodologies also place a heavy emphasis on
the user's role in the development process.
And both also emphasize the importance of team coherence.
So it seems that agile methods and user-centered design
agree on the most fundamental element, the importance of the user.
By comparison, the conflicts are actually relatively light,
at least in my opinion.
User-centered design disagrees with agile development on the importance of
documentation and
the importance of doing research prior to the design work actually beginning.
But, clearly, the methodologies have the same objectives.
They just disagree on how to best achieve them.
As a result, the authors advocate five principles for
integrating user-centered design and agile development.
Two of these were shared between the methodologies in the first place,
high user involvement and close team collaboration.
User-centered designs' emphasis on prototyping and the design life cycle
shows that by proposing that design is run a sprint ahead of developers to
perform the research necessary for user-centered design.
To facilitate this, strong project management is necessary.